<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Akshat Gupta</title>
    <link>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Akshat Gupta</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 09:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What are Diffusion Models?</title>
      <link>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/what_are_diffusion_models/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2024 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/what_are_diffusion_models/</guid>
      <description>Generative modeling is currently one of the most thrilling domains in deep learning research. Traditional models like Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) and Variational Autoencoders (VAEs) have already demonstrated impressive capabilities in synthetically generating realistic data, such as images and text. However, diffusion models is swiftly gaining prominence as a powerful model in the arena of high-quality and stable generative modeling. This blog explores diffusion models, examining their operational mechanisms, architectural designs, training processes, sampling methods, and the key advantages that position them at the forefront of generative AI.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fairness in Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/fairness_in_machine_learning_/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/fairness_in_machine_learning_/</guid>
      <description>As machine learning systems are increasingly used in critical areas like finance, employment, and criminal justice, it&amp;rsquo;s essential to ensure these models are fair and do not discriminate against certain groups. In this post, I will explore the concept of fairness in machine learning.
Defining Fairness Fairness in machine learning can be understood in several ways:
Group Fairness: This implies equal treatment or outcomes for different groups categorized by sensitive attributes like race or gender.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is a Vector Database?</title>
      <link>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/vector-databases/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/vector-databases/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve been working with modern AI systems — particularly in the realm of Large Language Models (LLMs), image embeddings, or recommendation engines — you&amp;rsquo;ve probably heard of vector databases. But what are they really? And why is everyone in the ML community suddenly so excited about them?
Let me break it down in simple terms, along with how I&amp;rsquo;ve been exploring them in my own projects.
🔍 The Problem: Why Traditional Databases Fall Short Traditional databases (like PostgreSQL or MongoDB) are great when you&amp;rsquo;re dealing with exact matches or relational queries:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is an Ontology in a Knowledge Graph?</title>
      <link>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/ontology-in-knowledge-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/ontology-in-knowledge-graphs/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re working with knowledge graphs, one term that keeps popping up is ontology. Sounds academic, right? Like something you&amp;rsquo;d find buried in a philosophy textbook.
But in the world of AI, data science, and search engines, an ontology is far from abstract — it&amp;rsquo;s the blueprint that gives your knowledge graph meaning. Let&amp;rsquo;s break it down and explore how it all fits together.
🧠 What Is an Ontology (in AI)?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Are Knowledge Graphs?</title>
      <link>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/what-are-knowledge-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://akshat4112.github.io/posts/what-are-knowledge-graphs/</guid>
      <description>We hear the term knowledge graph everywhere now — from Google Search to enterprise AI to GenAI apps. But what exactly is a knowledge graph, and why is everyone suddenly obsessed with it?
In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll break down knowledge graphs in plain language: what they are, how they work, and how I use them in my own projects.
🧱 The Basics: What Is a Knowledge Graph? At its core, a knowledge graph is a network of real-world entities (people, places, things) and the relationships between them.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
